<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Johan Basson - Java &amp; Web Developer</title><link>https://johanbasson.net/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Johan Basson - Java &amp; Web Developer</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 02:26:55 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://johanbasson.net/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What is CQRS?</title><link>https://johanbasson.net/posts/what-is-cqrs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2022 02:26:55 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://johanbasson.net/posts/what-is-cqrs/</guid><description>CQRS is a pattern where the write and read sides are split in an application, maximizing performance and scalability. CQRS is an abbreviation for Command, Query Responsibility Segregation. A CQRS application is composed of commands, queries, and events. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at the building blocks of a CQRS application.
The Write Side Aggregate
An Aggregate is a collection of one or more entities that can be seen as a single unit. For example an Order with line items, a Shopping Cart with each product and quantity.</description></item><item><title>Using Apache Kafka as an Eventbus in Spring</title><link>https://johanbasson.net/posts/kafka-eventbus-spring/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2022 16:46:50 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://johanbasson.net/posts/kafka-eventbus-spring/</guid><description>At some point, you may need to build an application(s) that reacts to events. This makes your application scalable as well as allows different parts to react to some event.
An example of such a use case is user registration. When a user is registered in the system you might need to send out an email welcoming the user. There might be a business case to provision his workspace or some required data initialization for the user to be able to use the system.</description></item><item><title>Java Record vs Lombok</title><link>https://johanbasson.net/posts/java-record-vs-lombok/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2022 16:46:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://johanbasson.net/posts/java-record-vs-lombok/</guid><description>What is Lombok?
Lombok is a 3rd party library that enhances Java with custom annotations. These annotations are added to a class or fields at code time.
At compile time, Lombok will transform a class file auto-generating code behind the scenes to make the life of a developer easier.
Let&amp;rsquo;s look at an example:
@Data class Person { private String firstName; private String lastName; } The @Data annotation of Lombok will generate getters, setters, equals, and hash and toString method.</description></item><item><title>Functional Principles applied to Java</title><link>https://johanbasson.net/posts/fp-applied-to-java/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2022 08:33:10 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://johanbasson.net/posts/fp-applied-to-java/</guid><description>Java is not a pure functional programming language, but we can apply the functional programming principles quite easily with it. Note the next example is my interpretation and implementation of applying functional programming principles.
Example Use Case We will build a simple endpoint that would perform an authentication of a user and if successful generate a JWT token for accessing our API. If the authentication is unsuccessful we will return an error.</description></item><item><title>Functional Programming Principles</title><link>https://johanbasson.net/posts/fp-principles/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 15:31:03 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://johanbasson.net/posts/fp-principles/</guid><description>Functional programming is a way to think about programs as a set of functions. It avoids concepts such as shared data and data mutation. By using Functional Programming principles we as developers can write better programs with much more stability. Let&amp;rsquo;s look at a few principles.
No side effects / Pure Functions A function is considered pure when it does not have any side effects. A function has side effects when its input does not always guarantee the same output.</description></item><item><title>SOLID Principles</title><link>https://johanbasson.net/posts/solid-principles/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 Jul 2022 12:57:03 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://johanbasson.net/posts/solid-principles/</guid><description>Software development is hard and there is a lot to know and understand in order to be a good developer. When it comes to Object Oriented Programming which is central to languages like Java and .Net, it becomes harder to build features using OOP, as you need to build everything using classes, objects, and properties.
We need to design classes, objects, and properties in a way which are easy to understand, easy to reason about, and above all, easy to maintain.</description></item></channel></rss>